Guide to the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Records ALBA.019
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Records
1933-2006
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade
ALBA.019
22.75 Linear Feet in 16 records cartons, 13 manuscript boxes, and 1 oversize folder
The organization Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) was founded in 1939 to provide aid and support for American veterans and Spanish refugees of the Spanish Civil War, and to advocate for democracy in Spain. Over the years, VALB provided a mechanism for veterans and their families and friends to maintain contact with each other, and also provided a public voice for the veterans and a focal point for political action. Eventually VALB devoted itself more and more to the preservation and dissemination of the veterans' history; the group sponsored publications and public events, cooperated in oral history projects and documentary films, and gathered the letters, photographs, memorabilia and other historical records that became the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archive. These records document the lives of individual veterans and the administrative and public activity of VALB from the organization's inception to the beginning of the twenty-first century.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Records were donated New York University in January 2001 by Brandeis University. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2007.002 and 1974.014. In 2017 the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigades sent an accretion of records from the Chicago post. The accession number associated with this gift is 2017.031. One box of records from the Bay Area post was added to the collection in 2018. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.018.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into four series. Matierals in Series I-III are arranged alphabetically by name of individual or topic. Series I: Spanish Civil War Materials has been further divided into two suberies; Subseries IA: Volunteers and Participants and Series IB: Subject Files. Series IV: Unprocessed has not been arranged by an archivist.
The series and subseries arrangement of the records is as follows: Series I: Spanish Civil War Era Materials; Sub-series IA: Volunteers and Participants; Sub-series IB: Subject Files; Series II: General Files; Series III: Scrapbooks; Series IV: Unprocessed
Historical Note
The origins of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) can be traced to a meeting that Steve Nelson, David McKelvy White and William Lawrence organized for veterans of the Spanish Civil War in New York City in December 1937. The Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade was officially formed two years later in December of 1939 when a constitution for VALB was adopted at the third National Convention of veterans. The Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (FALB), which had been the principal U.S. advocate for the American volunteers and Spanish Republicans during the Spanish Civil War, was disbanded at this time.
The "objects" of the organization, as stated in VALB's 1939 constitution, were to "keep alive the principles for which the Lincoln Brigade fought in Spain"; to assist in the medical and occupational rehabilitation of its members; to aid and advocate for all International Brigade prisoners still in Spain; to advocate for amnesty for "Republicans in Spain" and aid refugees of the Spanish Civil War; "to cooperate with all organizations and groups interested in promoting peace, democracy and civil liberties"; and finally "to maintain fraternal relations with organizations of veterans of the Spanish Republican Army in other countries."
From the end of World War II through the early 1960s, the leadership of VALB was often prevented from focusing solely on the organization's stated goals by the need to defend the organization from government charges of subversion. Dr. Edward Barsky, leader of the American medical volunteers in Spain during the Civil War and national chairman of the Joint Anti-Fascist Refugee Committee, was subpoenaed in 1946 to appear before the House Committee on Un-American Activities (HUAC). When he and his board refused to surrender financial records or to turn over the names of contributors and recipients of aid, Barsky was charged with contempt of Congress, convicted, and imprisoned. Veteran Steve Nelson was arrested in 1950 and put on trial for sedition. Nelson, along with Irving Weissman, was also arrested under the anti-Communist Smith Act and charged with subversion. Several veterans arrested under the Smith-McCarran Immigration Act in the 1950s faced deportation. A number of veterans were subpoenaed by HUAC, and ordered to testify as to whether or not they were or had been Communists. In 1953 VALB came under the scrutiny of the Subversive Activities Control Board (SACB), and two years later it was ordered to register with the United States Justice Department as a Communist-front organization. VALB refused and took the case to the Supreme Court. The Court decided in VALB's favor in 1968, but the VALB was not removed from the Attorney General's list of subversive organizations until 1971.
Threats from the Subversive Activities Control Board waned by the mid-sixties and thus freed from the costs, in time and money, spent on hearings and trials VALB expanded its reach. Although advocacy for Spanish refugees and political prisoners, and support for democratic reforms in Spain continued to be a primary interest, members of VALB pushed the organization to face other issues as well. The Civil Rights movement, Vietnam War protests, opposition to the proliferation of nuclear weapons, and support for the Sandinista rebels of Nicaragua were among the many issues and causes which VALB embraced.
From the 1960s and onward, the preservation and commemoration of the history of the Spanish Civil War became increasingly important to VALB. Members of VALB took part in reunions of the International Brigades in the German Democratic Republic, in Italy, and finally, after the death of Francisco Franco in 1975, in Spain. Members of VALB wrote memoirs and histories, gave interviews and recorded their reminiscences, lectured, took part in college symposiums, supported exhibits, and participated in film and television documentaries. The organization kept in touch with its multi-generational constituency through frequent mailings and through its newsletter, published in the early years under the title, The Volunteer for Liberty, and from 1957 as The Volunteer. In 1979 two archives for the Abraham Lincoln Brigade were established, a major one held at Brandeis University and administered by archivist, Victor Berch, and a smaller one at the University of California at Berkeley. The Brandeis collections were transferred to the Tamiment Library at New York University in 2001 and have since grown substantially through new donations. For many years VALB maintained an office at 799 Broadway in New York City; its last Secretary was Lincoln Brigade veteran Moe Fishman.
Provenance
This collection was created as part of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives (ALBA) originally housed at Brandeis University. The Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigades (VALB) donated their records to ALBA in the early 1990s. ALBA continued to add papers of individual veterans and associated organizations to Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigades (VALB) Records after the collection was acquired. New York University acquired the ALBA collections in November 2000, and this collection was transferred to New York University as part of that acquisition.
Scope and Content Note
The Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigades Records (dated 1933-2006) contain correspondence, writings, organizing files, and ephemera related to the operations of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigades (VALB) and activities of individual veterans during and after the Spanish Civil War. Records created during or around the time of the Spanish Civil War include correspondence and writings of nearly 80 volunteers and participants in the Abraham Lincoln Brigades, as well as articles, drafts, and news bulletins publicizing the political struggles in Spain. Many bulletins were created by organizations providing aid to the Spanish people or the Republican government including the American Medical Bureau, North American Committee to Aid Spain, Spanish Refugee Aid, and Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigades (FALB). Records created after the Spanish Civil War (1940-2006) include writings, subject files, correspondence, office files, clippings and ephemera documenting the lives of individual veterans, VALB events, regional VALB posts, and causes promoted by the VALB. Subject files document anniversary celebrations, commemorations and reunions, anti-Franco protests, political movements in Spain, and VALB’s struggles against the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC). The VALB Chicago Post is the most well documented regional post in the collection, which contains biographical data on Chicago area volunteers as well as organizing files related to Chicago area VALB events between 1995 and 2003. The Bay Area post is also well documented with an additional box of photographs, clippings, articles and ephemera form Bay Area events and voluteers. Also included in the collection are two scrapbooks documenting the early years of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln brigades, 1939-1952.
Separated Material
Photographs from the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Records have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library (ALBA PHOTO #15).
Typescripts.; Correspondence.; Biography files.; Articles.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Personal papers.; Printed ephemera.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Prisoners and prisons.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Fliers (printed matter); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Bay Area Post; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Spanish Refugee Relief Campaign; Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy; Fishman, Moses (Moe), 1916-; White, David McKelvy, 1901-1945; Bessie, Alvah Cecil, 1904-1985; Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Robeson, Eslanda Goode, 1896-1965.
- Series I: Spanish Civil War Materials, 1933-1946
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records created during or around the time of the Spanish Civil War. They include correspondence and writings of nearly 80 volunteers and participants in the Abraham Lincoln Brigades, as well as articles, drafts, and news bulletins documenting and publicizing the political struggles in Spain. Many bulletins were created by organizations providing aid to the Spanish people or the Republican government including the Medical Bureau, North American Committee to Aid Spain, Spanish Refugee Aid, and Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigades. Files of the Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigades (FALB) include letters to and from Eleanor Roosevelt, and documents regarding the efforts of Gypsy Rose Lee and Helen Hayes to aid the Spanish Refugees. Also of note are correspondence and reports regarding soldiers in the field, which include summaries of meetings, write-ups of individual soldiers, and notes regarding supplies, hospital conditions and transportation networks.
  - Subseries I:A: Volunteers and Participants, 1933-1946
    This subseries contains correspondence, writings, and ephemera of nearly eighty volunteers and participants in the Spanish Civil War. Of special note is a typescript of Eslanda Robeson's diary. Robeson kept this diary from January to February of 1938 when she accompanied her husband, Paul Robeson, on his tour to entertain the troops in Spain.
    - Altman, Israel, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Barr, Charles, undated, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
    - Bates, Ralph, undated, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bergamin, Jose, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Folder 4 Deleted, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Blair, John Clarence Alvie, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Block, Paul, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Burns, Paul, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Caldarella, Michael, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Caldarella, Michael: Correspondence (photocopies), 1937-1939, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Capadona, Bernard, undated, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Coon, John Cody, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Crotto, Sidney, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Cuiguerol, Alberto, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Delehanty, John A., 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Dorland, Norman, 1936, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Egg-Benes, Maria, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Eider, Louis, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Eloesser, Leo: "With the Army of Manoeuvre", 1938 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Fein, Richard, undated, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Freidman, Jack: Correspondence and Documents (photocopies), undated, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Frye, Peter, undated, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Gandall, Bill: Correspondence and Transcript (photocopies), 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Gellhorn, Martha, undated, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Gold, Irving, undated, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Goldblatt, Sana, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Goldstein, Milton, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Golomb, Ned: Passport, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Gross, Nathan, undated, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Gruskin, Harold, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Harris, Albert, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Harvey, Linda Joslyn: Poetry, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Haslan, Bob, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Holburn, Harry: Documents, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Hovan, John, undated, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Hovan, John: Correspondence, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Hughes, Langston, undated, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Humanes, Bernardo: Pass, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Hutchins, Evelyn Rahman, undated, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Hynes, Harold (with photograph), undated, Aug(?)1937-Sep 1938 (Box 2, Folder 6a)
    - Jenkins, Irving, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Keeler, Addison: Desertion Charge, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Keen, Harry, undated, 1937-1941, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Keith, Irving, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Kent, Rockwell, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Kupperman, Louis, undated, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Lamb, Constance Kyle, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Land, Sandford K., undated, 1935-1938 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Leinoff, Simon ( a.k.a. Thomas Lane), undated, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Leiviska, George: Diary (photocopy), 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Lustgarten, Larry: Ephemera, undated, 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - MacKay, Anthony (Antonio): Documents and Photograph (photocopies), undated, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Maki, Martin, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Mattson, Matti, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Mendelson, Wilfred: Correspondence, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Minor, Robert: "The Boys in Spain", undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Muller, John: Documents (photocopies), 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Negrin, Juan and Don Indalecio Prieto: Correspondence, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Nelson, Frank, undated, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Nelson, Steve: "In a Spanish Town", 1938 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Newman, Sol: Correspondence (transcriptions), 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Nin, Andres: "Reaction and Revolution" (typescript, translation), 1933 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Pacey, Donald, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Pacey, Donald: Leaflets/Flyers, undated (Box 2, Folder 29a)
    - Pulkkinen, George Albert: Greeting Card, French Line Tag and Card, Ephemera, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Rissanen, Tom, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Roach, Douglas, undated, 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Robeson, Eslanda: Diary, transcript, Jan 1938-Feb 1938 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Romer, Sam and Edna, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Rosenblatt, Sidney, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Ryant, Rubin: Correspondence (photocopies), undated, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Sachs, David, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Scarpello, Charles: "A Real Phony" (article, typescript), undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Seldes, George: article, draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Smith, David, undated, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Smith, David: Correspondence, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Steck, Robert: Memoir (photocopy), 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Taylor, Daniel, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Troxil, Stephen: Notebook, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Van Felix, William, undated, 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Vinovich, George Lawrence, undated, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Weinshank, Irving: Correspondence (photocopies), 1937-1939 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Weiss, Jacob: Stowaway, Imprisoned in England, May 1938-Jun 1938 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Witt, Bert, undated, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Subseries I:B: Subject Files, 1936-1940
    This subseries includes articles, drafts and translations of articles, and news bulletins that were used to publicize the plight of the Spanish people and build support for the Republican cause; appeals and bulletins of several organizations that provided aid for the Spanish people and awareness of the Republican cause in Spain including the Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy and the Spanish Refugee Relief Campaign; and extensive files of the Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (FALB) that contain correspondence, minutes and information regarding FALB's efforts to support the American volunteers, veterans and the Spanish people. Letters to and from Eleanor Roosevelt are included in the FALB files; documents regarding the efforts of Gypsy Rose Lee and Helen Hayes to aid the Spanish Refugees are also in this sub-series. Also of note are correspondence and reports regarding soldiers in the field and prisoners. Reports from the field include summaries of meetings, write-ups of individual soldiers, and notes regarding supplies, hospital conditions and transportation networks.
    - American Friends of Spanish Democracy: Medical Bureau, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - American Friends of Spanish Democracy: Press Releases and Statements, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - American Friends Service Committee, undated, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - American League against War and Fascism, 1937, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Auto Park (Volunteers of): Souvenir Letter (with photo postcards) of Thanks for a Contribution, Nov 25, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 23a)
    - Auxilio Social, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Barcelona Blood Transfusion Service, Apr 1939 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Bombardment, undated, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Bombardment: Balloon Defense, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Bombardment: Report, The Daily News, Nov 9, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Bulletins: Articles and Reports, undated, 1936-1939 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Bulletins: Articles and Reports, Spanish, undated, 1937-1940 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Bulletins: Cult-Commission of the Internationals [sic] Brigades of the Center of Murcia, Jul 1937-Aug 1937 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Bulletins: Franco, articles and drafts, undated, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Bulletins: Federated Press, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Bulletins: Hora de Spain, drafts, undated, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Bulletins: Independent News(Service de Presse Hebdomadaire du Bureau d' Informations Franco-Britanniques), 1937-1939 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Bulletins: Information Bulletin, undated, 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Bulletins: El Liberal, undated, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Bulletins: Servicio de Informacion, Apr 1937-May 1937 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Bulletins: Servicio de Informacion, articles and documents, undated, 1936 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Bulletins: Socialist, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Bulletins: El Socialista, articles and translations, undated, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Bulletins: El Sol, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Bulletins: Spain, Reports and Statistics, ca.1937 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Bulletins: Spanish Embassy, Bureau of Information, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Bulletins: Spanish Information Bureau, undated, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Bulletins: Speeches and Statements, undated, 1937, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Bulletins: Universidad Popular F. U. E. de Madrid, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Catalonia: Flyers and Articles, undated, 1937-1939 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Catalonia: Comissariat de Propaganda, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Catalonia: Partido Socialista Unificado (P.S.U.) Calendar (photocopy), 1938 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Catholic Church, undated, 1937-1938 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Christian Front: "Spain in Arms" (film flyer), 1939 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Ciudad de Barcelona (ship): Account of Sinking (typescript, in French), undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Clergy Responses, undated, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Clippings and Articles (SCW), undated, 1936-1939 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Clippings: Spanish and French, 1936-1939 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence, undated, 1931, 1936-1938 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence: Barsky, Dr. Edward, undated, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence: White, David McKelvy, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Death Notices, undated, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Diary: Fragment, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Dies Committee: VALB Counter-Offensive, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Embargo, Campaign to Lift, undated, 1938-1939 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Embargo, Campaign to Lift: David McKelvy White, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Ephemera: Money and Stamps, undated, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Ephemera: Support Activity, undated, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Ephemera: Travel, undated, 1937-1938 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Faraynikter Yidisher Hilfs-Komitet far Shpaniye, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Flushing Joint Committee for Aid to Spain, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Articles and Appeals, Drafts, undated, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Cigarettes, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Clippings, undated, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Correspondence, undated, 1937-1939 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Correspondence, Eleanor Roosevelt, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Embargo, undated, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Ephemera, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Leaflets and Flyers, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Minutes, 1937-1939 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Miscellaneous, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Organizing, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Play, Alice Henry, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Poem, Alexander Lang, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade: Press Releases, undated, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 17)